Harold Gould Henderson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Harold Gould Henderson Papers 1918-1955 (bulk 1937-1946)
MSS83960
Henderson, Harold Gould
500 items
1 container
.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author and professor of Japanese art and culture. Born 1889; died 1974. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, military papers, and printed material pertaining to Henderson's service during World War II as chief of the Japanese Language Section of the Allied Forces South West Pacific Area Psychological Warfare Branch and following the war as head of the Education Division of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers Civil Information and Education Section in occupied Japan.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Henderson, Harold Gould.
Organizations
Allied Forces. South West Pacific Area. Psychological Warfare Branch. Japanese Language Section.; Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. Civil Information and Education Section. Education Division.
Subjects
Art, Japanese.; Education--Japan.; Educational change--Japan.; Emperors--Japan.; Haiku.; Japanese literature.; Psychological warfare.; World War, 1939-1945--Oceania.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Psychological aspects.
Places
Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.
Provenance
The papers of Harold Gould Henderson, author and professor of Japanese art and culture, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Mary Benjamin Henderson, in 1985 and 1991.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Harold Gould Henderson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harold Gould Henderson (1889-1974) span the years 1918-1955, with the bulk of the material dating from 1937 to 1946. The papers consists of correspondence memoranda, military papers, reports, notes, translations, drafts of writings, and printed matter. They document Henderson’s service during World War II as chief of the Japanese Language Section of the Allied Forces South West Pacific Area Psychological Warfare Branch, and later as head of the Education Division of the Civil Information and Education Section, Supreme Command for the Allied Powers, in occupied Japan. Included are reports and notes on wartime propaganda leaflets and on postwar education reform. The papers also contain Henderson’s account of having drafted a clause in the imperial rescript delivered on 1 January 1946 in which the emperor renounced his divinity. The collection further consists of Henderson’s writings on Japanese art and literature, some of which he wrote while teaching Japanese art and culture at Columbia University between 1935 and 1944. Included are his English translations of Japanese haiku poems, principally those of Matsuo Bashō and Yosu Buson. Henderson’s several books on haiku, beginning with The Bamboo Broom: An Introduction to Japanese Haiku (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co, 1934) popularized the poetic genre in America.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General, 1945-1955, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ledoux, Louis V., regarding Tōshūsai Sharaku, 1937-1938, undated (Box 1)
- United States Army (Box 1)
  - Memoranda and orders, 1918-1920, 1943-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1944-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Reports and translations, 1942-1945, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - “Secret History of the Japanese Emperor’s Renunciation of Divinity,” 1947 (Box 1)
- Writings and translations by Henderson and others (Box 1)
  - Art, 1937, undated (Box 1)
  - Haiku, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Japanese grammar and dictionaries, undated (Box 1)
  - “Suan Ki,” astronomical instrument, undated (Box 1)